Finding Aid for Gene Thurber papers, 1967-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Gene Thurber papers 1967-1990
Thurber, Gene
4 linear feet
2012171 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of James Thurber (donor no. 10815 ) and came to the library in August 2012.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Gene D. Thurber (1926-2010) was a special education administrator and consultant. In the 1970s he was a consultant in the Special Education Division of the Michigan State Department of Education. He also served as a member of the Michigan Special Olympics Board of Directors (1969-1982) and as Director of Special Education for Kent County (1978-1990).
The Gene Thurber collection consists of reports and studies and other materials received on the topic of special education in Michigan. A significant portion of the collection concerns his work with the Kent Intermediate School District. Very few items in the collection were authored by Thurber.
Subjects:
Thurber, Gene.; Michigan Association of Intermediate Special Education Administrators.; Michigan. Dept. of Education.; Michigan. Special Education Service Area.; Kent Intermediate School District.; Special Olympics Michigan (Organization); Special education--Michigan.
- Kent Intermediate School District, 1978-1990
  (Thurber was administrative assistant for operations in special education for the district)
  - Reports, planning materials, policy statements, needs assessment (Box 1)
- Michigan Special Olympics, 1979-1983
  - Programs (scattered issues), brochures, planning materials (Box 1)
- Vocational Education Special Education Project, 1970s
  - Program guide and various manuals designed to assist special education teachers in developing instructional plans for handicapped students (Box 2)
- Michigan Association of Intermediate Special Education Administrators, 1967-1973
  - By-laws, minutes of meetings, and related materials (Box 3)
- Michigan Department of Education, Special Education Services
  (Thurber was instructional specialist and mentally impaired program consultant)
  - Competency-based instructional materials (Box 3)
  - Institute on Secondary Programming (Box 3)
  - Objectives for Elementary Programming (Box 3)
  - Inclusive Education in Michigan (Box 3)
  - Michigan Council for Exceptional Children, Annual Convention, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Career Education Handbook for Implementation (Box 3)
  - Secondary Education Career Manual (Box 3)
  - Institute of the Study of Michigan Experimental Programs for the Educationally Handicapped (Box 3)
  - Career Education for the handicapped Person (Box 3)
  - Special Education Task Force Report, February 1978 (Box 3)
  - "Development and Implementation of Secondary Special Education Programs" 1975 (Box 3)
  - Teacher Competencies Task Force (Box 4)
  - Workshop: Special Education / Career Education Field Test, 1976 (Box 4)
  - Proposed model guidelines for secondary special education programs, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Observation and client evaluation in workshops; a guide and a manual, 1972 (Box 4)
  - Special Education Code Development (Box 4)
  - Muskegon Area Learning Program (Box 4)
  - Recommended Prevocational Competencies for Special Education in [various areas] (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 4)
Related Material
The library also has the records of the Society for the Preservation of Michigan Special Education History and the papers of Lynwood Beekman who was closely associated with special education legislation in Michigan.